Guide to the Manchester Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Albums, 1697/98 Feb 8; Series I
  - Sir P. Medows to the E of M, describing proposals of the Imperial Court for the despatch of reinforcements to Spain, and the position of the Duke of Savoy's affairs. The French had been "Contriving to get Fribourg into their hands, and 100,000 livres was the price set, but the commander, a Swiss, was too honest for them, and gave General Thungen notice from time to time, so that if they had proceeded to put their design in execution, the 22nd of the last month they had cost the Imperialists powder and ball." Vienna, 1708 Feb. 4 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, to the effect that the issue of the deliberations of the Diet, and the real designs of the French respecting Neufchâtel were still in uncertainty. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 512) Bern, 1708 Feb 5 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - J. Addison to the E of M, giving the numbers in the division in the House of Lords on the dissolution of the Scotch Privy Council. "This day," he adds, "being the Queen's birthday, there has been a great appearance at Kensington, and will be a greater this evening. Her Majesty did not come to town, and has not ordered any ball or comedy," which they say will be reserved for H.R.H.'s birthday. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 275) Cockpit, 1708 Feb 5 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - S. Edwin to the E of M, on the state of parties, the Court, the proceedings in the House of Lords relating to the Scotch Privy Council and Lord Peterborough, etc. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 270) Exchequer, 1707/08 Feb 6 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - J. Addison to the E of M, confiding to him the dismissal of Mr. Secretary Harley, and the appointment of a committee of Lords to examine Gregg, and "other State criminals," especially Valiere, who, having been employed by Harley as "an owler," had carried on a secret correspondence between the French Court and some of their friends in this country. The final debate in the House of Lords on the abolition of the Scotch Privy Council is also described. Mr. Boyle was to succeed Harley, and would be succeeded at the treasury by the Speaker. (Printed, without date, in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 278), 1708 Feb 7 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - J. Chetwynd to the E of M, mentioning the enthusiasm excited at Turin by a picture of Queen Anne, announcing his re-call, and asking for the Earl's interest and protection. Turin, 1708 Feb 11 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, on proceedings related to the proposed neutrality of Neufchâtel. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 513) Bern, 1708 Feb 12 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - J. Addison to the E of M, announcing the appointment of Mr. Boyle as Secretary, and mentioning various rumours of other appointments. "It is said Mr. Harley and his friends had laid scheme to undermine most of our great officers of the State, and plant their own party in the room of 'em. If we may believe common fame, he himself was to have been a peer and Lord Treasurer... It is, I believe, very certain that the Duke of Marlborough and Lord Treasurer refused to sit any longer in council with so wily a Secretary, and would have laid down themselves, if he had not been removed. It is said he had hopes of working his ends by the assistance of a Bed-chamber woman, whom, it seems, he has found out to be his cousin." (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 280), 1707/08 Feb 13 (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Sir James Montague [Montagu] to the E of M, on family matters, and on the recent changes of office, the dismissal of Mr. Harley, "for setting up a faction against my Lord Duke of Marlborough and Lord Treasurer," his own expected promotion to be Attorney-General, etc. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne, ii, 282), 1708 Feb 17 (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - The Earl of Sunderland to the E of M, instructing him to press the treaty of commerce upon the Venetians, and to give no encouragement to the Duke of Mantua. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 515) Whitehall, 1707/08 Feb 18 (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - J. Chetwynd to the E of M, announcing that he expected to be succeeded by Mr. Palmes, and giving some particulars relative to the Duke of Savoy. Turin, 1708 Feb 19 (Box 13, Folder 25)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, on the prospects of arranging a neutrality for Neufchâtel. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 513) Bern, 1708 Feb 19 (Box 13, Folder 26)
  - J. Addison to the E of M, on various proceedings in the House of Lords and Commons. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 284), 1707/08 Feb 20 (Box 13, Folder 27)
  - J. Vanbrugh to the E of M, on the opera in London. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 289) London, 1707/08 Feb 24 (Box 13, Folder 28)
  - J. Addison to the E of M, on the opera, and on debates in the Commons. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 291), 1707/08 Feb 24 (Box 13, Folder 29)
  - J. Chetwynd to the E of M, announcing that the investiture of Montferrat, etc, had been conceded to the Duke of Savoy by the Court of Vienna, but that it was unlikely he would succeed in obtaining the Novaresse in compensation for money advanced on the Emperor's account. Some details respecting the movements of the fleet are added, with an unfavourable opinion of the expedition to Spain. Turin, 1707/08 Feb 14/25 (Box 13, Folder 30)
  - Sir P. Medows to the E of M, chiefly upon the terms upon which the Court of Vienna was willing to grant investiture of the Palatinate, etc. Count Staremberg's luggage was on its was to Italy. The Duke of Marlborough, it was expected, would meet Prince Eugene at Hanover "for their concerting measures." At Ratisbon it had been agreed to borrow 1,000,000 crowns and to take 3,000 Saxons into the service of the Empire. Vienna, 17078 Feb 25 (Box 13, Folder 31)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, on various aspects of the Neufchâtel affair. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 515) Berne [Bern], 1708 Feb 26 (Box 13, Folder 32)
  - J. Addison to the E of M. "This day the Committee of Lords make report of their examination of the State Criminals..." Cockpit, 1707/08 Feb 27 (Box 13, Folder 33)
  - J. Addison to the E of M, on Parliamentary business and on the great naval preparations made by Great Britain against the expected French invasion in the interests of the Pretender. The Postscript only is in Addison's hand: "My eyes being out of order, I am forced to make use of another hand." (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 296), 1707/08 Mar 2 (Box 13, Folder 34)
  - The E of M to the Lord Treasurer, expressing his belief that little good was to be effected at Venice, and that the alliance of the Venetians was of little worth, could it even be obtained. Affairs at Vienna were managed by Cardinal Lambert, Prince Eugene, and Count Wratislaw. The Prince would not go to Spain, but would meet the Duke of Marlborough at the Hague. The chief hope of the allies must be fixed upon his Grace. The Earl expresses his thanks for the Privy Seal giving him his plate, and calls attention to the sum due to him from the Treasury. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 298) Venice, 1708 Mar 2 (Box 13, Folder 35)
  - Speech of the E of M [apparently to the Doge of Venice.] (Printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 481, where the probably correct date assigned is Sep. 22, 1707), n.d. (Box 13, Folder 35a)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Montagu, acquainting him with the arrival of Lord Hinchinbrook at Venice, and offering suggestions respecting the future movements of the young man who had more life and spirit than powers of application, and who had recently had a difference with M. La Come, which had been accommodated by the Earl. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 309) Venice, 1708 Mar 2 (Box 13, Folder 36)
  - J. Chetwynd to the E of M, thanking the Earl for his protection and advice. Marshal Staremberg was, according to advices from Vienna, "the person designed for Spain," whither more Imperial troops would be sent. It was, however to be feared the Duke of Orleans would make his footing in Spain so good that it would be no easy matter to dislodge him. An enclosure relating to the affairs of Savoy is mentioned. Turin, 1707/08 Mar 3 (Box 13, Folder 37)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, on various matters relating to the proposed neutrality of Neufchâtel. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 516) Berne [Bern], 1708 Mar 4 (Box 13, Folder 38)
  - J. Addison to the E of M, on proceedings in Parliament., 1707/08 Mar 5 (Box 13, Folder 39)
  - Sir P. Medows to the E of M, chiefly on the proceedings at a meeting of the states of Hungary at Pressburg. Some arrivals at Vienna, and some appointments to the Imperial army in Catalonia are noticed, as well as some acts of violence committed by Hungarian malcontents. Vienna, 1708 Mar 7 (Box 13, Folder 40)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, on matters relating to Neufchâtel. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 517) Berne [Bern], 1708 Mar 7 (Box 13, Folder 41)
  - J. Addison to [the E of M] on proceedings in Parliament., 1707/08 Mar 9 (Box 13, Folder 42)
  - J. Addison to [the E of M] on proceedings in Parliament. Cockpit, 1707/08 Mar 12 (Box 13, Folder 43)
  - J. Addison to [the E of M] on proceedings in Parliament. Cockpit, 1707/08 Mar 16 (Box 13, Folder 44)
  - The E of M to the Duchess of Marlborough, recommending a Venetian musician to the notice of the Duchess, and of the Queen. (Draft. Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 321) Venice, 1708 Mar 16 (Box 13, Folder 45)
  - Letter (unsigned and unaddressed) containing an account of a circular letter of the King of France, on the occasion of the projected invasion of Scotland, and some particulars of the expedition, and of the Pretender's movements. (In French. See A. Stanyan to the E of M, 50) Geneva, 1708 Mar 16 (Box 13, Folder 46)
  - Henry Newton to the E of M, to the effect that he had little news to mention except the arrival of a ship from Turkey, which had been captured by a Zealand privateer. Leghorn, 1707/08 Mar 16 (Box 13, Folder 47)
  - J. Vanbrugh to the E of M, regretting that Great Britain had trusted too much her navy, and that there were no land forces in Scotland to meet the projected invasion. The news that Admiral Byng was in sight of the French fleet, however, led to the belief that no landing would be effected. The Duke of Marlborough had letters from Paris to the effect that "this project was opinionated by the King of France, against the opinion of others; which would incline one to think if it did not succeed one way he wished it would another, by getting rid of the Pretender, which is likely enough to happen." There is also some discussion of operatic matters. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 318) London, 1707/08 Mar 16 (Box 13, Folder 48)
  - John Scudamore to the E of M, on damask velvets wanted by the Duchess of Marlborough, and the price of marble chimney-pieces. The English fleet at Gibraltar was short of provisions. Genoa, 1708 Mar 17 (Box 13, Folder 49)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, mentioning enclosure of a letter from Geneva, which purported to give an account of the French project for the invasion of Scotland. (See 46. The greater part of the letter, but without the enclosure, is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 518) Bern, 1708 Mar 18 (Box 13, Folder 50)
  - Sir P. Medows to the E of M, on the Emperor's approval of the Resolution of the Diet, the religious affairs of the Empire, the proceedings of the Hungarian malecontents, the departure of Prince Eugene for Holland, the proposal that England should transport 6,000 Germans from Italy to Catalonia at her own expense, the insufficiency of the forces supplied by the Emperor, and the proposal to make Bucari a free port. (pp. 7) Vienna, 1708 Mar 21 (Box 13, Folder 51)
  - J. Vanbrugh to the E of M, on the buildings in progress at Kimbolton. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 320) Stevenage, 1707/08 Mar 22 (Box 13, Folder 52)
  - E. Howe to the E of M, on the preparations of Hanover for the forthcoming campaign. Hanover, 1708 Mar 22 (Box 13, Folder 53)
  - J. Addison to [the E of M], giving some small items of news, including the arrest of the Duke of Hamilton. The French squadron was supposed to have "got into some of the ports of Norway." (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 328), 1707/08 Mar 23 (Box 13, Folder 54)
  - Colonel Broune de Camus to the E of M, recommending to his favour an Irish gentleman named Hurly, who wished to serve as captain of cavalry in the British army in Spain. (In French) Pavia, 1708 Mar 24 (Box 13, Folder 55)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, on difficulties arising out of the neglect of the King of Prussia to pay the Swiss troops in Neufchâtel, etc. (The principal part is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 518) Berne [Bern], 1708 Mar 25 (Box 13, Folder 56)
  - J. Addison to the E of M, giving various small items of news. Mr. Stanhope was appointed Envoy Extraordinary to the King of Spain, and Major-General commanding the British forces in Catalonia. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 327), 1708 Mar 26 (Box 13, Folder 57)
  - J. Addison to the E of M on proceedings in Parliament. Cockpit, 1708 Mar 30 (Box 13, Folder 58)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, to the effect that an agreement would probably be made for the neutrality of Neufchâtel. (Printed, with the exception of a postscript dated April 1, on the subject of the Dunkirk Squadron, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 521) Bern, 1708 Mar 31 (Box 13, Folder 59)
  - J. Addison to the E of M on proceedings in Parliament. Cockpit, 1708 Apr 2/13 (Box 13, Folder 60)
  - Thomas Pritchard to the E of M, on domestic matters. London., 1708 Apr 6 (Box 13, Folder 61)
  - The Earl of Sunderland to the E of M, informing him of the Queen's resentment when she learned that an affront had been put upon him at Venice. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 524) Whitehall, 1708 Apr 6/17 (Box 13, Folder 62)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, informing him that a new project for the neutrality of Neufchâtel would in all probability be ratified. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 523) Bern, 1708 Apr 8 (Box 13, Folder 63)
  - J, Addison to the E of M, touching briefly on various matters of gossip... The Government was calling on suspected persons in Scotland, including the Duke of Atholl, to make their appearance. The Venetian Ambassador had been forbidden the Court. Several merchants thought a fitting reparation for the affront put upon the Earl at Venice would be free importation of English cloth there... Cockpit, 1708 Apr 9 (Box 13, Folder 64)
  - J. Addison to the E of M, to the effect that the Venetian Ambassador had received "with great uneasiness and something like resentment" the message forbidding him the Court until the Earl had received reparation for the insult at Venice. Parliament was prorogued for a fortnight, and would probably be suddenly dissolved. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 343) Cockpit, 1708 Apr 13 (Box 13, Folder 65)
  - The Duchess of Marlborough to the E of M, on musical matters. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 337) St. James, 1708 Apr 13 (Box 13, Folder 66)
  - J. Chetwynd to the E of M, mentioning a report which had reached him of a defeat of a French fleet by Sir George Byng. He had no news of importance to communicate. Turin, 1708 Apr 14 (Box 13, Folder 67)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, announcing that the French King's ratification of the neutrality of Neufchâtel was expected, and suggesting that satisfaction should be demended of the Pope for assistance rendered to the Pretender. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 524) Bern, 1708 Apr 15 (Box 13, Folder 68)
  - J. Addison to [the E of M], announcing the arrival in London and committal to the Tower of Lord Griffin, Lord Middleton's two sons and other persons arrested as accomplices in the late attempt of the Pretender. "The people were with much ado restrained from outraging them as they passed the streets." Fifty more state prisoners of distinction were expected. Mr. Smith was made Chancellor of the Exchequer. The factory at Borneo had been "ruined by the natives." He concludes: "It is said that the G. Duke furnished the Pope with the money that he gave the P.P. of Wales. If so, his Minister here will quickly hear of it." (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 348) Whitehall, 1708 Apr 20 (Box 13, Folder 69)
  - Lord Halifax to [the E of M]. He would always espouse Lord Manchester's interest though "sensible there were those who did desire" they "should not be well together." Everything would be done to obtain satisfaction for the insult to Lord Manchester at Venice. Lord Sunderland had "talked very roundly" to the Venetian Ambassador who had sent a Memorial in justification. Nothing short of a "public satisfaction" would be accepted. (Printed, in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 349), 1708 Apr 20 (Box 13, Folder 70)
  - Copy of a letter (without signature) apparently to the E of M, on behalf of the Abbate Paolo Franceschini. (In Italian) Venice, 1708 Apr 21 (Box 13, Folder 71)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, expressing fears that the affairs of Toggenburg would give even more trouble than those of Neufchâtel (now believed to be settled), and explaining the religious and other difficulties of the case. (The principal part is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 525) Bern, 1708 Apr 22 (Box 13, Folder 72)
  - The Duke of Würtemberg to the E of M, asking for authentic information respecting the issue of the French expedition to Scotland, concerning which there were contradictory reports. He hoped it was true that the "Chevallier Bings" [Byng] had obtained a considerable advantage. He had orders to proceed to H.R.H. at Turin, and thence to Susa to take command of a corps there. (In French) Mirandola, 1708 Apr 27 (Box 13, Folder 73)
  - E. Howe to the E of M, announcing the arrival of the Duke of Marlborough and Prince Eugene at Hanover. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 526) Hanover, 1708 Apr 29 (Box 13, Folder 74)
  - The Earl of Sunderland to the E of M, mentioning enclosure of a Memorial from the Venetian Ambassador, with the answer to it. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 529) Whitehall, 1708 Apr 23 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - General Cadogan to the E of M, mentioning enclosure of a circular which showed the progress of preparations for the campaign. The Duke of Marlborough was expected at Brussels, and the Duke of Vendôme at St. Amand. Regular accounts of the movements in the fields would be sent to the Earl by Mr. Cardonnel. Brussels, 1708 May 3 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - The Earl of Sunderland to the E of M, informing him that the Queen desired he should have the fullest reparation for the affront put upon him at Venice, and leave that place if he failed to obtain satisfaction. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 527) Whitehall, 1708 Apr 20 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - J. Chetwynd to the E of M, giving an account of the various preparations made, and being made, for sending succours into Spain. Mr. Stanhope was expected. The Venetian Ambassador, passing through Turin, had failed to see H.R.H., who wished to have as little as possible to do with the Republic. Mr. Chetwynd asked for the Earl's interest with the Ministers. (pp. 6) Turin, 1708 May 8 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, It was not known that the ratifications of the Treaty of Neutrality for Neufchâtel had yet been exchanged. The differences respecting Toggenburg would probably be satisfactorily adjusted, so that the inhabitants could be secured in the free enjoyment of their religion and liberties. It was to be hoped that the Earl would, before leaving Venice, obtain satisfaction for the affront offered him "in visiting his gondola and what is more, plundering it." The Earl would naturally be "little obliged to Mr. Brown that drew him into the difficulty." Bern, 1708 May 6 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - J. Chetwynd to the E of M. Mr. Stanhope had arrived, but was "almost as much in the dark" as Chetwynd himself about the expected reinforcement of 5,000 Imperial troops for Spain. He had written very pressingly on the subject both to the Duke of Marlborough and to Lord Sunderland. The delays of the Imperialists were causing uneasiness. "Mr. Palmes" would pass through Venice on his way to Turin. Perhaps, the Earl could ascertain Mr. Chetwynd's "destiny" from him. Turin, 1708 May 8/19 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - General Palmes to the E of M, to the effect that he hoped to conclude his negotiation at Vienna, and proceed to Italy in a few days. Vienna, 1708 May 9 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - The E of M to Prince Hercolani, informing him that he was about to start for Vicenza, an the following day, on his return home and that a complete rupture with Venice was imminent. The Duke of Marlborough and Prince Eugene were both at Hanover, and the Duke would not return to England but join the army at once. (Draft. In French) Venice, 1708 May 10 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - S. Edwin to the E of M. Correspondence was difficult, as letters were commonly opened, if not intercepted on the way. The Duke of Hamilton had been bailed, and would, in all probability, be "one of the sixteen peers for Scotland." Sir James Montagu was not yet made Attorney-General. The Whigs were stronger in Parliament by 44 votes since the last election, and the Tories and Jacobites much dejected... Exchequer, 1708 May 11 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - J. Vanbrugh to the E of M, chiefly on operatic affairs, but with the following postscript: "My Lady Marlborough goes now very often to Court, and is in perfect good humour. I hope all will keep right." (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 354) London, 1708 May 11 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - H. Boyle to the E of M, acknowledging the Earl's congratulations offered to him upon his appointment as Secretary. London, 1708 May 11 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, touching briefly on various matters. (Printed, in part, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 352) Bern, 1708 May 13 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Philippo Hercolani to [the E of M]. He expected to be at Mantua on the 21st, and to go on thence to Milan. He thanked the Earl for procuring him the protection of the Queen, and an employment in which he might be useful to the common cause. He hoped to receive letters from the Earl at Milan, and would then endeavour to conclude a business which should awake in the Court of Vienna sentiments consistent with the Imperial dignity. He had never been guilty of any base action in his life, and would not enter upon one now that he had the honour to serve His Imperial Majesty. (In Italian) Crocetta, 1708 May 15 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Valeriano Pellegrini to the E of M, announcing that he was about to set out for Düsseldorf in the following week. (In Italian) Verona, 1708 May 17 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Marlborough, expressing the belief that the Duke would be the deliverer of this country, and that reparation would be made for the affront offered to himself at Venice. (Copy) Venice, 1708 May 18 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - James Stanhope to the E of M, on the prospect of the campaigns in Flanders and Catalonia. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 533) Savona, 1708 May 18 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - S. Edwin to the E of M. "The Title of Dover" was not to be given to "Mr. Massam," but to the Duke of Queensborough. The elections had been favourable to the Whigs. There would be another attempt to make Lord Somers and Sir James Montague [Montagu] President of the Council and Attorney- General. A sea expedition with ten regiments from England and Ireland, and the great naval preparation of the Dutch were much talked of. Exchequer, 1708 May 18 (Box 14, Folder 17)